<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-25T16:21:50+00:00</updated><id>https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A cocktail corner</title><subtitle>Tracking cocktail recipes, ideas, and experiences </subtitle><entry><title type="html">[R&amp;amp;D] Sparkling Lychee Soju</title><link href="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-carbonated-lychee/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[R&amp;amp;D] Sparkling Lychee Soju"/><published>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-carbonated-lychee</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-carbonated-lychee/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lychee">Lychee</a> is a great fruit that I tend to associate with late spring and summer. It’s sweet, fragrant, and fresh tasting, and it’s not too hard to find in major US cities (either at an Asian grocery store or specialty food store). For a while I have been thinking of incorporating lychee into summer cocktails. Back in college I found a bottle of lychee liqueur in a liquor store in Chicago’s Chinatown. It was a quite versatile liqueur, although the lychee flavor did get muted over time. Recently, I’ve seen a few options for lychee liqueurs available in major liquor stores in the USA, but I haven’t tried them out yet. However, one common “hack” for a drink that tends to go around as the Lychee Martini at many restaurants is to simply use syrup from canned lychees (Amazon options: [<a href="https://amzn.to/4c8n1ZI">1</a>, <a href="https://amzn.to/3Ys7D78">2</a>]).</p> <p>Thus, recently an idea crossed my mind to make my own flavored soju by mixing clear soju and lychee syrup from a can. However, to further amp up the summer vibes I decided to carbonate the whole mixture to turn it into sparkling lychee soju that can be used on its own or to top off cocktails.</p> <h3 id="sparkling-lychee-soju"><a href="/cocktails/infusions-recipes/sparkling-lychee-soju">Sparkling Lychee Soju</a></h3> <ul> <li>375 ml unflavored soju (~16.5% ABV)</li> <li>200 ml lychee syrup (from a can of lychees)</li> </ul> <p>Chill soju in the fridge ahead of time (this should help with carbonation). Combine all ingredients in an <a href="https://amzn.to/46CHzZi">iSi whipper</a> and charge with one <a href="https://amzn.to/3A71ByZ">CO2 cartridge</a>. Shake a few times and put into the fridge for 30 to 45 minutes. After the wait, degas the container and add one more CO2 cartridge. Shake a few times and put into the fridge for at least 1 hour and up to overnight. Degas the container, then unscrew the top and pour into cocktail of choice. Carbonation will keep a day or two if you keep resealing the container, but it’s best to use the whole batch within a few hours for maximum effervescence.</p> <hr/> <p>With the carbonated lychee soju in hand we can make a few fun cocktails.</p> <h3 id="lychee-cocktail-v1"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/lychee-cocktail-v1">Lychee Cocktail v1</a></h3> <ul> <li>1 oz white rum</li> <li>0.75 oz lemon juice</li> <li>1 barspoon 2:1 syrup</li> <li>4 oz sparkling lychee soju</li> </ul> <p>Shake all ingredients except the soju with ice and double strain into a chilled coupe glass. Top off with sparkling soju and optionally garnish with a single lychee fruit (no pit).</p> <p>The drink is bright and floral with acidity form the lemon helping offset the sweetness of lychee soju. I used a very neutral Flor de Caña white rum for this drink, but I believe it can be made more interesting by using a mild agricole rum (e.g. <a href="https://www.rhums-dillon.com/nos-gammes/rhums-blancs/rhum-blanc-dillon-40deg">Dillon Rhum Agricole Blanc 40% ABV</a>) instead.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-cocktail-1-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-cocktail-1-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-cocktail-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-cocktail-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h3 id="lychee-spritz-v1"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/lychee-spritz-v1">Lychee Spritz v1</a></h3> <ul> <li>0.5 oz lime juice</li> <li>0.5 oz Falernum</li> <li>3 oz sparkling lychee soju</li> </ul> <p>Combine lime juice and Falernum in a well-chilled glass and stir briefly to mix. Top off with sparkling lychee soju. Alternatively, you can build this drink over pebble ice in a rocks glass in the same manner.</p> <p>I prefer this made up, since Falernum and lychee experience a unique marriage of flavors that yields multi-layered floral aromas and a nuanced interplay of spices, sweetness and light tartness.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-spritz-1-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-spritz-1-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-spritz-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-spritz-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h3 id="lychee-rum-punch-v1"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/lychee-rum-punch-v1">Lychee Rum Punch v1</a></h3> <ul> <li>1 oz Jamaican overproof white rum (<a href="https://www.williampricedistilling.com/spirits">William Price 124 proof</a>)</li> <li>0.5 oz <a href="https://alpenz.com/product-batavia.html">Batavia Arrack</a></li> <li>0.25 oz Jamaican Pot Still Black Rum (<a href="https://www.caribbean-spirits.com/labeldetails.php?id=52">Hamilton</a>)</li> <li>0.5 oz Falernum</li> <li>0.75 oz lime juice</li> <li>4 oz sparkling lychee soju</li> </ul> <p>Combine all ingredients except the soju in the shaker and shake with ice. Strain into a Collins glass packed with crushed ice. Top off with lychee soju and optionally garnish with a lychee fruit.</p> <p>The mix of rums is strong and funky so the extra dilution from crushed ice is needed to keep this drink balanced. The sparkling soju top off keeps the aromas floral and fresh creating an interesting layering of flavors.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-rum-punch-1-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-rum-punch-1-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-rum-punch-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/lychee-rum-punch-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <p>Overall the sparkling lychee soju seems to be a versatile ingredient that can be made quickly and used for a variety of cocktails. I believe that beyond the pairing with Falernum and rums, it would also pair well with gin based drinks by interacting with other botanicals. One thing of note is that most sojus available in groceries are not the most fine spirits, and the unflavored variety tends to be rather harsh tasting. Using a better soju can yield a smoother product to work with, so hunting down a good unflavored soju might be the next logical step.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-and-development"/><category term="lychee"/><category term="carbonation"/><category term="soju"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Making DIY flavored soju with a twist]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Flippin’ good</title><link href="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/flipping-good/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flippin’ good"/><published>2024-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/flipping-good</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/flipping-good/"><![CDATA[<p>Flips are a interesting and unusual category of cocktails. While it’s not uncommon to see an egg white being added into a shaken cocktail [<a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/double-lemon-whiskey-sour">1</a>] for a nice frothy top, but the usage of a whole raw egg is mostly reserved for rare holiday treats like eggnog. Flips are the cocktails that fill this gap. They tend to feature bold aromatic dark spirits (dark rums, brandies) often accompanied by heavy cream and always a whole raw egg. The addition of the egg yolk produces rich cocktail that often feels like a dessert in a glass. Thus, it’s not surprising that most often flips appear as the last drink of the night aka nightcap, and are more often featured in the dessert section of a menu.</p> <p>In this post we will explore some classic flips, personalized variations on those, and some more experimental modern cocktails. Note, all of the cocktails listed here are also featured in the <a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes">cocktail recipes collection</a> on this website.</p> <h2 id="cocktails">Cocktails</h2> <h3 id="rum-flip"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/rum-flip">Rum Flip</a></h3> <p>This is an old time classic flip that can accommodate a variety of rums. I prefer to use dark Jamaican rum here for a more bold and complex profile.</p> <ul> <li>1.5 oz dark rum</li> <li>0.5 oz heavy cream</li> <li>0.25 oz 2:1 syrup</li> <li>1 whole egg</li> </ul> <p>Combine all ingredients in a shaker and shake without ice. Add ice and shake again, strain into a coupe glass. Garnish with freshly grated nutmeg.</p> <p>I swapped 0.5 oz of the dark rum for blackstrap rum for a more molasses forward drink. The result is pleasant with coffee and chocolate notes from the dark rums and nice silky texture from the egg.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/rum-flip-1-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/rum-flip-1-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/rum-flip-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/rum-flip-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h3 id="rum-flip-v2"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/rum-flip-v2">Rum Flip v2</a></h3> <ul> <li>2.75 oz Jamaican rum</li> <li>0.25 oz allspice dram</li> <li>1 tsp 2:1 Demerara syrup</li> <li>1 whole egg</li> </ul> <p>Dry shake all ingredients, then add ice and shake again. Strain into a coupe and garnish with grated nutmeg.</p> <p>Surprisingly light drink despite having a whole egg in it. Allspice nicely comes through without overtaking the drink.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="porto-flip"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/porto-flip">Porto Flip</a></h3> <ul> <li>1.75 oz ruby port</li> <li>1 oz cognac</li> <li>1 oz heavy cream</li> <li>1 whole egg</li> <li>1.5 tsp extra-fine sugar</li> </ul> <p>Dry shake all ingredients, then add ice and shake again. Strain into a coupe, optionally add a barspoon of yellow Chartreuse and garnish with grated nutmeg.</p> <p>This cocktail is smooth and silky with port wine taking the front seat. The cognac shows up in the aftertaste, while Chartreuse and nutmeg give this drink a festive spicy aroma preceding every sip.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/porto-flip-2-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/porto-flip-2-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/porto-flip-2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/porto-flip-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h3 id="coffee-cocktail"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/coffee-cocktail">Coffee Cocktail</a></h3> <p>This is a classic flip which owes its name to a look rather than an ingredient (<a href="https://www.liquor.com/recipes/coffee-cocktail/">it has no coffee</a>). Compared to a more modern Porto flip this drink has an equal ratio of cognac and ruby port, and doesn’t include any cream.</p> <ul> <li>1 oz cognac</li> <li>1 oz ruby port</li> <li>1 whole egg</li> <li>0.5 oz 2:1 syrup</li> </ul> <p>Dry shake all ingredients, then add ice and shake again. Strain into a coupe and garnish with grated nutmeg.</p> <p>This cocktail is similar to the Porto flip, but with a sweeter and creamier feeling. The port is more pronounced in the beginning while the cognac shows in the aftertaste.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/coffee-cocktail-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/coffee-cocktail-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/coffee-cocktail-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/coffee-cocktail.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h3 id="cynar-flip"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/cynar-flip">Cynar Flip</a></h3> <p>This recipe is due to Jayce Kadyschuk from <a href="https://clivesclassiclounge.com/">Clive’s</a> in Victoria, British Columbia. I found it on <a href="https://www.liquor.com/recipes/cynar-flip/">Liquor.com</a> while taking a deeper dive into modern flips.</p> <ul> <li>1 oz rye whisky</li> <li>1 oz Cynar</li> <li>0.5 oz Cointreau</li> <li>0.25 oz clove 2:1 syrup</li> <li>1 whole egg</li> </ul> <p>Dry shake all ingredients, then add ice and shake again. Strain into a coupe and garnish with grated nutmeg.</p> <p>The drink is very bold thanks to the 100 proof rye whisky and Cynar, but rich and creamy at the same time. This flip has a nice balance of bitterness, sweetness and rich mouthfeel that seems appropriate for a nightcap.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/cynar-flip-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/cynar-flip-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/cynar-flip-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/cynar-flip.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <p>By a coincidence, a few nights ago <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/C8hi_s6JllR/">a reel</a> with a flip cocktail in it popped up on my Instagram feed. I wasn’t able to quickly find a full reference for this but the description credits Sam Ross <a href="https://www.instagram.com/samueljoelross/?hl=en"><i class="fa-brands fa-instagram"></i></a>. This looked like a fun drink to make, especially since I have a bottle of homemade banana liqueur lying around at the moment.</p> <h3 id="bourbon-banana-flip"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/bourbon-banana-flip">Bourbon Banana Flip</a></h3> <ul> <li>1.5oz bourbon</li> <li>0.75oz banana liqueur</li> <li>0.5oz 2:1 syrup</li> <li>0.5oz heavy cream</li> <li>1 whole egg</li> </ul> <p>Dry shake all ingredients, then add ice and shake again. Strain into a coupe and garnish with grated nutmeg.</p> <p>The drink turned out very pleasant albeit a touch too sweet for my taste. Bourbon comes through and banana flavor is present, but subtle. This is a great dessert drink recipe and a good use of banana liqueur, I am very glad that <a href="https://www.instagram.com/deadendwest/?g=5">@deadendwest</a> reel brought this drink to my attention.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/bourbon-banana-flip-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/bourbon-banana-flip-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/bourbon-banana-flip-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/bourbon-banana-flip.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h2 id="concluding-remarks">Concluding Remarks</h2> <p>Despite using a whole egg flips are not as heavy as a serving of a good eggnog. In fact, they feel noticeably more airy and light than expected, while still having a silky rich mouthfeel. Furthermore, due to a healthy helping of other ingredients these cocktails have no trouble handling bold flavors and intense spices. Thus, they present a perfect opportunity to experiment with your favorite complex amaro or unusual funky spirit.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cocktail-collections"/><category term="flip"/><category term="egg"/><category term="port"/><category term="cynar"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discovering old and new flips]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[R&amp;amp;D] Clove Syrup</title><link href="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-clove-syrup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[R&amp;amp;D] Clove Syrup"/><published>2024-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-clove-syrup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-clove-syrup/"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I wanted to make <a href="cocktails/cocktail-recipes/cynar-flip">Cynar Flip</a> cocktail which calls for clove simple syrup. The recipe I <a href="https://www.liquor.com/recipes/cynar-flip/">found online</a> originally called for a preference based amount of cloves simmered in water which is then used to make a 1:1 syrup. Looking a bit more around the web, I found two more recipes: <a href="https://www.foodandwine.com/recipes/clove-syrup">one</a> calling for 1.5 tsps of cloves which are then coarsely ground and boiled in the water used to make a 1:1 syrup, and <a href="https://imbibemagazine.com/recipe/clove-syrup-recipe/">the other</a> calling for 1/3 cup of whole cloves and a simmer of all ingredients together for a 1:1 syrup.</p> <p>All of the above recipes share two commonalities that I wanted to challenge for the syrup I wanted to make. First, I am used to working with 2:1 syrups due to their shelf-stability, and hence I am more familiar with calibrating recipes based on sweetness of a 2:1 syrup. Second, recently I started dabbling into making tinctures and extracts that can be added in minute (using a dropper) amounts to flavor large volumes, thus opening the door to making flavored syrups by combining tincture/extract with neutral 2:1 syrup base. In particular, the reasoning for the second design choice comes from the observation that 2:1 syrup is typically abundant in my setup and is shelf-stable, analogously a tincture is also shelf stable, and hence, we can make small batches of flavored syrup when we need it, instead of making and storing a large amount of a flavored syrup. In the case of clove syrup this is particularly appealing since there aren’t many drinks that call fo rit explicitly.</p> <p>Thus, we will be testing two recipes for 2:1 clove syrup side by side, the first recipe will follow the boil and infuse strategy, while the second recipe will involve adding small amount of clove tincture to the 2:1 syrup base.</p> <h3 id="clove-syrup-v1">Clove Syrup v1</h3> <ul> <li>10 g cloves (about 1.5 tbsp)</li> <li>0.5 cup water</li> <li>1 cup sugar</li> </ul> <p>Coarsely grind the cloves and combine with sugar and water in a pot. Simmer on medium heat occasionally stirring until the sugar dissolves. Take of the heat and let infuse covered for 30 minutes to an hour. Strain, filter and bottle.</p> <hr/> <h3 id="clove-syrup-v2">Clove Syrup v2</h3> <ul> <li>6 g cloves (about 1 full tbsp)</li> <li>60 ml neutral grain spirit (75.5% ABV)</li> </ul> <p>Coarsely grind the cloves and combine with the grain spirit in a small glass jar. Let the mixture infuse for at least 48 hours, after two weeks filter out the solids and bottle.</p> <p>Use 10 drops per standard cocktail.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="comparison">Comparison</h2> <p>I combined 2 oz of water with 0.5 oz of clove syrup (v1), and 0.5 oz of regular 2:1 syrup and 10 drops of clove tincture (v2) for tasting purposes. Both syrups had strong clove aromas with the tincture based one being a touch sharper and brighter on the nose. However, once tasted the v1 has an evenly incorporated clove flavor that carried throughout the whole mixture, while v2 had less persistent taste. Furthermore, v2 tasted overall sweeter with sugar syrup having a more clear presence.</p> <p>Overall for the cocktails, I believe that for a few ingredients stirred cocktails, as well as for flips the v1 is the way to go. For the drinks with the clove aroma is of essence, but the prolonged clove flavor is not as important the v2 is a better alternative.</p> <hr/> <p>As a bonus feature I decided to add a few cocktails I have recently made with either of the syrup options.</p> <h2 id="cocktails">Cocktails</h2> <h3 id="clove-sour-v1"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/clove-sour">Clove Sour v1</a></h3> <ul> <li>1.5 oz bourbon (Wild Turkey 101)</li> <li>1 oz lemon</li> <li>0.5 oz clove syrup v1</li> <li>0.25 oz Fernet Branca</li> </ul> <p>Shake all ingredients with ice and strain into a chilled coupe.</p> <p>The cocktail turns out quite fresh and acidic with a light touch of spice and herbal complexity.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/clove-sour-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/clove-sour-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/clove-sour-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/clove-sour.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <hr/> <h3 id="baking-spice-sour-v1"><a href="/cocktails/cocktail-recipes/baking-spice-sour">Baking Spice Sour v1</a></h3> <ul> <li>1 oz bourbon (Wild Turkey 101)</li> <li>1 oz rye whiskey (Rittenhouse 100)</li> <li>0.75 oz lemon juice</li> <li>0.5 oz maple syrup</li> <li>0.25 2:1 syrup</li> <li>15 drops clove tincture</li> <li>15 drops Angostura bitters</li> </ul> <p>Shake all ingredients with ice and strain into a chilled coupe.</p> <p>This drink starts out surprisingly mellow, but quickly unravels layers of spice with clove from tincture and cinnamon and allspice from the Angostura bitters. The rye whiskey split base helps it maintain crispy spice, while the bourbon and syrups mellow out the finish balancing the acidity. You can also swap bourbon for applejack for an apple pie flavored cocktail perfect for an autumn evening.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/baking-spice-sour-1-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/baking-spice-sour-1-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/baking-spice-sour-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/baking-spice-sour-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-and-development"/><category term="clove"/><category term="syrup"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Building robust and shelf-stable clove syrup]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[R&amp;amp;D] Limoncello (pt. 1)</title><link href="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-limoncello-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[R&amp;amp;D] Limoncello (pt. 1)"/><published>2024-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-limoncello-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-limoncello-1/"><![CDATA[<p>We will be using <a href="https://www.kevinkos.com/post/lemoncello-easier-n-cheaper">Kevin Kos’s</a> proportions for making limoncello. The main experiment will consist of comparing the results from fresh lemon peels to the one obtained with the lemon peels used to make lemon super juice.</p> <h2 id="main-recipe">Main recipe</h2> <ul> <li>35 g lemon peels</li> <li>210 ml neutral grain spirit (75.5% ABV)</li> <li>315 ml water</li> <li>105 g sugar</li> </ul> <p><strong>Target ABV:</strong> ~30%; <strong>Target sugar (g/L):</strong> 200</p> <hr/> <p>Combine lemon peels with the grain spirit in a jar and seal tightly. Let sit for 2 to 3 days periodically shaking the jar to stir around the contents. Combine sugar with water and stir to dissolve, then add infused spirit (filtering out the peels). Stir all ingredients together and bottle. Limoncello will instantly get cloudy.</p> <h2 id="fresh-vs-reused-peels">Fresh vs reused peels</h2> <p>I made a batch of lemon superjuice with 35 g of peels, and then after blending the superjuice together, filtering and bottling, I retained the processed peels. From there onwards th two recipes are identical in ingredients and infusion times. Unsurprisingly the fresh peel limoncello is a lot brighter in color, so it wins the presentation game.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-2-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-2-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-2-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><em>Limoncello from peels used to make lemon superjuice.</em></p> <p>What’s more interesting is that the reused peel limoncello still tastes reasonably good. However, it has a slightly artificial lemon flavor akin to that in bad flavored vodkas or cheap lemonades. I suspect this off flavor comes from the trace amounts of citric acid that likely got carried over from the superjuice process with the peels. The amount is not enough to make the final product sour, but it is enough to add a slightly chemical aftertaste to the drink.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-1-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-1-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/limoncello-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><em>Limoncello from fresh lemon peels.</em></p> <p>The fresh peel limoncello is bright not only in its color but in the aroma and flavor as well. It also has a nice long finish from the extracted lemon oils. It is pleasant to drink on its own as a desert liqueur, but of course we will try to make a few cocktails with it as well.</p> <h2 id="cocktails">Cocktails</h2> <p>A super simple sipper we can make with limoncello is simply combining 2 ounces of limoncello with about 6 oz of tonic water in a Collins glass with a bunch of ice. The drink is refreshing, but quite complex thanks to the bitterness of the tonic and lemon essential oils in the limoncello. This is a great long drink for a hot summer and it could pair well with light vegetable appetizers or a nice cheese plate.</p> <p>Now, that we have a simple summer drink down let’s explore the possibilities offered by limoncello. The first challenge I wanted to solve in making a more complex cocktail featuring limoncello was addressing the acidic component of the drink. Conceptually there are a few ways this can be solved: (1) double down on the lemon and use juice, (2) become <del>Sprite</del> “lemon-lime soda” and use a different citrus juice, or (3) use a non-citrus source of acidity. All of these solutions have their time and place, but I didn’t want to do either (1) or (2). The lemons on lemons just doesn’t sound too appealing at the moment, and the lemon-lime combination usually feels like a generic citrus flavor in so far as it muddies the nuance of the individual citrus used.</p> <p>With all this being said, this section is largely experimental, and hence results may vary. If you are looking for a less creative, but more stable cocktail <a href="#double-lemon-whiskey-sour">jump here</a>.</p> <p>Now, what are some alternative souring agents we could use? I made a <a href="/cocktails/syrups-recipes/strawberry-superjuice/">strawberry superjuice</a> before, and it’ll likely work well with limoncello for a pink lemonade inspired cocktail. Given that limoncello is sweet, but still far from a syrup, I suspect that the following cocktail could work:</p> <h3 id="pretty-pink-palette">Pretty Pink Palette</h3> <ul> <li>1 oz gin</li> <li>1.5 oz limoncello</li> <li>1 oz strawberry superjuice</li> <li>1 barspoon 2:1 syrup</li> </ul> <p>Now, a fair warning is that this cocktail hasn’t been tested yet, so proportions might need to get tweaked a bit. I also suspect that putting the result into a Collins glass, topping of with soda and garnishing with a nice mint sprig/bunch would end up quite well.</p> <p>Another alternative souring agent is hibiscus. Hibiscus not only provides a spectacular shade of purplish red to any liquid it touches, but also acidifies the infusion making it a nice way to build a sour. There are different ways to integrate hibiscus into a cocktail, but I’ll go with the simplest option and just brew a quick hibiscus tea on the side first. We will use about 20 grams of dried hibiscus for about 1.5 cups of boiling water. After combining we will let the tea steep for about 10-15 minutes.</p> <h3 id="hibiscus-lemonade-v0-bad">Hibiscus Lemonade v0 (bad)</h3> <ul> <li>1 oz gin</li> <li>1.5 oz limoncello</li> <li>1 oz hibiscus tea</li> <li>1 barspoon 2:1 syrup</li> </ul> <p>The drink turns a nice shade of purple red, but it doesn’t taste good. Several things go wrong here at once: (1) limoncello ends up being too sweet and the hibiscus tea simply can’t balance it in these proportions; (2) the ABV in this drink ends up quite high, which doesn’t work too well with a more subtle hibiscus tea. We can rectify these problems by adjusting ingredient proportions.</p> <h3 id="hibiscus-lemonade-v1">Hibiscus Lemonade v1</h3> <ul> <li>1 oz gin</li> <li>1 oz limoncello</li> <li>2 oz hibiscus tea</li> <li>1 barspoon 2:1 syrup</li> </ul> <p>This version tastes more balanced and closer to a typical sour. It has nice hibiscus front and long lemon finish thanks to the limoncello. I am not fully satisfied with this drink even though it is definitely a solid attempt at a summery limoncello cocktail. I believe that a way to make this both more balanced and more exciting would require making a non-sweetened Sorel and using it in place of hibiscus tea. I might try this idea later in the future.</p> <p>However, similarly to what I’ve mentioned for the strawberry version I believe that this can be made into an even more summery highball by adding soda water. Unlike the strawberries, the hibiscus doesn’t seem to pair with mint that well in my perception, so we will skip that component. Furthermore, instead of adding soda water to our cocktail, we will make a more diluted version of the cocktail and then carbonate the whole thing in an iSi whipper with some CO2 cartridges. At some point in the future I probably will write a more detailed post about carbonation, but for now we will follow a simple guide:</p> <ol> <li>Cocktail in the iSi whipper goes into fridge for at least 30 minutes</li> <li>Add 1 cartridge CO2, shake, release gas, back to fridge for at least 30 minutes.</li> <li>Add 1 more cartridge CO2, shake, release gas, back to fridge for at least 30 minutes and ideally overnight.</li> <li>Degas, unscrew top and pour into glass.</li> </ol> <p>The adjusted recipe scaled to yield roughly 600 ml of the total carbonated cocktail is below.</p> <h3 id="carbonated-hibiscus-lemonade">Carbonated Hibiscus Lemonade</h3> <ul> <li>3 oz gin</li> <li>4 oz limoncello</li> <li>1 oz lemon juice</li> <li>6 oz hibiscus tea</li> <li>6 oz water</li> </ul> <p>The end result is a lot better than the previous two versions. The two CO2 charges make the drink quite fizzy. Lemon leads the flavor profile, but the hibiscus is noticeable. As with all the other cocktails in this post the aftertaste is mostly lemon oils. Overall this is a pleasant summer cocktail that can be pre-batched for a party. It has nice complexity and very appealing color, and carbonation adds a bit of extra fun for the presentation.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/cocktails/assets/img/carbonated-hibiscus-lemonade-1-480.webp 480w,/cocktails/assets/img/carbonated-hibiscus-lemonade-1-800.webp 800w,/cocktails/assets/img/carbonated-hibiscus-lemonade-1-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/cocktails/assets/img/carbonated-hibiscus-lemonade-1.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><em>Carbonated hibiscus lemonade.</em></p> <hr/> <p>Finally, we will wrap with a modified whiskey sour by doubling down on lemon flavors. While this is a lot less interesting since we are using lemon juice alongside our limoncello, it still yields a fun cocktail with a reasonably new twist.</p> <h3 id="double-lemon-whiskey-sour">Double Lemon Whiskey Sour</h3> <ul> <li>1 oz bourbon</li> <li>1 oz rye whiskey</li> <li>1.25 oz limoncello</li> <li>1 oz lemon juice</li> <li>0.5 oz Amaro Montenegro</li> <li>1 dash Angostura bitters</li> <li>1 egg white (optional)</li> </ul> <p>If using egg white dry shake first, then shake all ingredients with ice and strain into a Nick and Nora glass.</p> <p>I am currently trying the version without egg white and it has a nice bright acidic bite to it. The whiskeys interplay well with the ingredients with the light spice of rye aligning with amaro and bitters. The lemon flavor is bright in the beginning and transforms into a nice lemon oil aftertaste. Depending on personal preferences a barspoon or two of 2:1 syrup can make this cocktail a bit more balanced for some people.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-and-development"/><category term="citrus"/><category term="liqueur"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Basics of limoncello]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">[R&amp;amp;D] Bloody Mary</title><link href="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-bloody-mary/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="[R&amp;amp;D] Bloody Mary"/><published>2024-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-bloody-mary</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://nsapoval.github.io/cocktails/blog/2024/rnd-bloody-mary/"><![CDATA[<p>A canonical Bloody Mary for me consists of three elements: (1) tomato juice, (2) spice, (3) umami. Clearly there are many ways to get these components into a drink, and thus like many classic template cocktails Bloody Mary is open to essentially infinite variations on the theme. Most of the ideas I am planning to test now have been around for a while. First, using kimchi for adding complexity with a touch of spice (and thus, satisfying point 2; see: [<a href="https://www.foodandwine.com/recipes/kimchi-bloody-mary">1</a>, <a href="https://imbibemagazine.com/recipe/kimchi-bloody-mary/">2</a>]). Second, using fino sherry to compliment tomato flavor [<a href="https://imbibemagazine.com/elements-tomatoes/">3</a>]. Finally, deriving some additional umami from soy sauce and a touch of MSG. Thus, this experiment is not about discovery of a new flavor combination of profile, but rather an exercise in polishing and adjusting those flavors for personal taste.</p> <h2 id="tomato-base">Tomato base</h2> <p>I started by grabbing a can of whole peeled tomatoes (roughly 800 g total) and adding 100 g kimchi, 35 g dark soy sauce, and about 1 g of MSG. After blending all ingredients together I gto my first iteration of the tomato base. I decided to give it a go in a tomato base heavy basic variation on Bloody Mary as follows:</p> <h3 id="bloody-mary-v21">Bloody Mary v2.1</h3> <ul> <li>2 oz blanco tequila</li> <li>6 oz tomato base</li> <li>0.75 oz lemon juice</li> <li>1 barspoon 2:1 syrup</li> <li>3 dashes celery bitters</li> </ul> <p>The drink ended up being balanced and pleasant, but I felt that the kimchi did not contribute enough spice, and its flavor was lacking. Hence, I decided to adjust the tomato base proportions and up the kimchi content to bring its flavors into the focus and amplify the spice kick.</p> <h3 id="tomato-base-v02">Tomato Base v0.2</h3> <ul> <li>1 can whole peeled tomatoes (~800 g)</li> <li>250 g kimchi</li> <li>35 g dark soy sauce</li> <li>~1 g MSG</li> </ul> <p>The modified tomato base hit the flavor profile I wanted, being bright and having a distinct kimchi bite. The resulting product is a very chunky sauce rather than a smooth tomato juice you can get from the store. This didn’t make measuring out volumes more difficult, but I do suspect that this base might end up more heterogeneous. Beside using a better blender it is possible to opt for tomato juice instead of canned tomatoes in this recipe. However, from a practical standpoint of a home kitchen + bar I found it much more convenient to work with canned tomatoes (which I tend to have in my pantry) as opposed to tomato juice.</p> <h2 id="cocktails">Cocktails</h2> <p>With the tomato base being adjusted to my liking, I was happy to continue on the quest of optimizing Bloody Mary options. For the next iteration of the cocktail I wanted to first tune down the amount of the tomato base, since with a stronger kimchi flavor it would overpower the drink at a 6 oz pour. Furthermore, I wanted to work in some fino sherry, which on its own is a rather tricky ingredient to work with, but it tends to compliment vegetal flavors quite well. Thus, I arrived at the following cocktail:</p> <h3 id="bloody-mary-v22">Bloody Mary v2.2</h3> <ul> <li>2 oz blanco tequila</li> <li>1 oz fino sherry</li> <li>3 oz tomato base</li> <li>0.75 oz lemon juice</li> <li>1 barspoon 2:1 syrup</li> <li>3 dashes celery bitters</li> </ul> <p>The resulting cocktail is a lot more funky than the first draft. Kimchi flavor pops through and the spice is there to flesh out what I consider a Bloody Mary basic trait. The sherry is quite subtle, it is still possible to distinguish its key characteristics in the background, but on the forefront the cocktail is very much a vegetal and bright Bloody Mary.</p> <p>With the classic version of the Bloody Mary being more or less in the space I wanted it to be in, I decided to see if I can push the tomato base a bit further. The first idea that came to my mind was making something closer to an equal parts cocktail featuring sherry and tomato base. Given that the tomato base already has some acidity from the tomatoes and kimchi, and some added salinity from the soy sauce, a straight equal parts cocktail would likely end up too sour. Thus, I opted to curb down the lemon juice and keep it at 0.75 oz pour. Additionally, similarly to what I’ve been doing before I’ll keep adding 1 barspoon of 2:1 syrup to keep the flavors balanced. Finally, I wanted to switch the base spirit in order to give sherry more room without sacrificing too much of the botanical notes, thus I swapped tequila for gin.</p> <h3 id="bloodied-gin">Bloodied Gin</h3> <ul> <li>1 oz gin</li> <li>1 oz fino sherry</li> <li>1 oz tomato base</li> <li>0.75 oz lemon juice</li> <li>1 barspoon 2:1 syrup</li> <li>1 dash celery bitters</li> </ul> <p>Surprisingly while only having 1 ounce of the tomato base this cocktail yielded the boldest kimchi flavor. Furthermore, the sherry is a lot more prominent and compliments the tomato and fermentation notes from the base. Being more acidic makes this cocktail less of a salad in a glass, and more of a proper aperitif that can be consumed before the meal or alongside the appetizers (I’d pair some carpaccio, steak tartare or burrata with this cocktail).</p> <p>Generally, at this point I am pretty happy with the experiment, and got at two cocktails that I’d like to serve to other people, and keep for my own records. However, so far we have been mostly experimenting with the classic recipes or relatively fail-safe formulas. In the spirit of true R&amp;D session we need to take this further by descending into <del>radical sandwich anarchy</del>[<a href="https://flowingdata.com/2017/05/02/sandwich-alignment-chart/">4</a>] cocktail madness.</p> <h2 id="one-step-further">One step further</h2> <p>What we got so far with the Bloodied Gin cocktail is a tart, slightly spicy, vegetal aperitif. Now, let’s do two things at once, first we will try to amplify sherry making it the center spirit of the drink, and second we will turn this drink from chunky salsa to a clear and refined beverage.</p> <p>We will attempt to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=74fsCUdQAtw">milk clarify</a> a part of our cocktail and then combine the clarified drink with fino sherry. For the clarified part we will need:</p> <ul> <li>2 oz gin</li> <li>2 oz tomato base</li> <li>1.5 oz lemon juice</li> <li>0.25 oz 2:1 syrup</li> <li>3 dashes celery bitters</li> </ul> <p>We will combine all of these ingredients together and then pour them over 2 ounces of milk. Lightly stir the mixture after combining, since some of the cocktail might not be well exposed to milk due to its chunky consistency. Let the mixture sit for 30 minutes, and then filter it through strainer + nut milk bag + coffee filter setup.</p> <p>Filtering milk and cocktail mixture takes a lot longer than with a bigger batch of whiskey sour or rum punch that I’ve done before. I am not sure if that’s due to the more solids present in the mix or due to the smaller sieve and hence tighter fit of the filtering layers.</p> <p>At this stage the milk clarified portion of the drink has a characteristic pizza smell to it owing to mixture of milk and canned tomatoes.</p> <p>For the final cocktail assemble:</p> <ul> <li>2 oz clarified mixture</li> <li>1 oz fino sherry</li> </ul> <p>Stir the ingredients with ice and pour into a coupe glass. The result is quite acidic and bright. There is no spiciness in this drink, but the fermented flavors of the kimchi carry through. The sherry is a lot more pronounced compared to the previous version, which fit sour design choices. Unlike clarified punches and sours this drink doesn’t seem to have the smooth and silky mouthfeel despite the milk clarification. Overall this is a step in an interesting direction, but quite far from a finished cocktail.</p> <p>A few options for future trials could include making a clarified and acid adjusted tomato juice and infusing a base spirit with kimchi.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research-and-development"/><category term="bloody-mary"/><category term="kimchi"/><category term="spicy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Optimizing Bloody Mary recipe(s)]]></summary></entry></feed>